校对: -俄刻阿诺斯，逐丶风，烈之斩，Dr_ScRuB，Fabio
翻译，时间轴，压制: Bolshevik0
本视频上传于2018.07.22
下划线是我没听清且我认为自动字幕有问题的原文
When we think of anime today is hard to ignore one aspect
谈到今天的动画 有一个方面不容忽视
that has seemingly taken over the medium as we know it in the modern day, Moe.
就是看上去已经被萌元素控制了
Moe anime, Moe girls, Moe shows.
萌动画 萌妹子 萌节目
Whether it be a star, or genre, or just a feeling
不管是偶像 还是萌题材 还是感觉上
is hard to explain exactly what Moe is to an uninformed outsider.
很难对外行人解释萌 的含义
Yet anyone familiar with anime will grow to have an unspoken understanding of it.
当然任何熟悉动画那一套的人都对此有一种说不清的理解
Because it is everywhere.
因为它无处不在
Nowadays Moe absolutely dominates anime
现在萌元素统治了动画
but it wasn't always like this.
但以前不是这样
In fact it's something that many of you may have witnessed the rise of yourself
事实上许多人见证了萌元素的发展
within the very life span of your anime fandom.
哪怕只是你入坑动画的这么一段时间内
How did such a vague broad concept rise to prominence
如果此粗糙模糊的概念是如何变得这么广为人知
to become synonymous with the modern anime culture.
同时和现代动画相伴相生
How long has Moe been around for anyway
萌的风潮到底发展了多久
and how is it evolved over the years?
这些年来它又是如何演化的
Today I wanted to tell the story of Moe.
今天我想讲讲萌元素的故事
How its journey led to it taking over the medium as we see it today
它又是如何统治了今天的动画
and maybe unravel the secret formula behind what seems to be just cute anime girls.
也许能解释如何成为二次元萌妹子的神秘方法
This is
这就是
萌的革命
To understand where Moe came from, we first need to understand what Moe actually is.
搞清楚萌元素的来历之前要先搞清楚萌的定义
And that's easier said than done.
当然说话总比行动要容易
Aside from it having something to do with making your Kokoro Go Doki Doki Literature Club,
不提如何创建你自己的心动文学俱乐部
it's been very commonly debated as to how Moe is truly defined.
萌元素的定义至今仍广受争议
Now I don't think we just can be able to grab an Oxford English Dictionary off the shelf
当然我不认为能从书架上的牛津英语词典里
and find a hard definition of what Moe is.
找到萌的定义
注: Urban Dictionary 意思是城市词典
So maybe we can use the next best thing, Urban Dictionary.
也许Urban Dictionary 更适合
Moe is when your heart gets a boner.
萌就是你的内心bó起了
Huh, that's... that's... that's actually pretty accurate.
呃 这挺准的
Wait sir, if you're female, does that mean Moe characters make your heart go Moe?
等下先生 如果你是妹子 难道说萌角色让你内心bó起了
Exercise the idea that Moe is when your heart gets the bonus,
关于萌能让人内心愉悦的这个定义
pretty much the one sentence definition I normally settle on when describing it to strangers.
差不多就是我给决定给陌生人的一句话解释
But I think it's cause a feeling of affection or attraction towards a specific character
但我认为这是某种对特定角色魅力的解释
or character traits that comes from a place of innocence.
或者某种天真无邪的小孩子的性质
Some may describe it as a burning desire to protect a character.
有些人会把这个解释成想拼命保护某个角色的欲望
Some may describe it as character features that evoke a deep endearment.
有些人解释成某些角色的特征导致了强烈的喜爱之情
Some may describe it as just cute.
有些人只认为这就是可爱
It's very subjective for the most part
多数都是非常主观的看法
as if you're really inclined anything can be Moe.
就好比你可以认为任何东西都是萌的
Even Guts or Donald Trump could be Moe.
甚至格斯或者川普也可以是萌的
吐槽: 标准尬双关，名字是Moe
Even Moe could be Moe, Moe Szyslak.
甚至辛普森一家 里的莫·希斯拉克也可以是萌的
The exact definition is not so much as important to see how anime characters have evolved over the years
与其探究萌的确切定义 不如研究这些年来动画角色身上发生的改变
to more effectively capture this emotion and attachment to a mass audience.
这些改变产生的原因则是为了更好地让大多数观众爱上动画角色
And with that in mind how far do the roots of Moe a traced back to.
那么萌的根源又在哪里
萌的起源
For such a vague concept it's hard to point to a specific origin point
对于如此模糊的概念 实在难以指出精确的起源
as it could be argued that the idea of constructing characters
同样需要指出的是
with the goal of eliciting an intimate responsive affection is as old as the medium itself.
动画打一开始就有引起观众对角色产生亲密的喜爱之情的角色塑造手段
However I think a good place to start is looking for early character traits and tropes
当然 一开始去找早期角色的性格特征是比较合适的
which would eventually evolve into what we know as modern Waifu culture.
而这些性格特征最终演变成了现在的二次元老婆文化
As it is, the audience attachment to these trace
正因如此 观众喜欢的这些特征
that would be refined and grow into the Moe we know today.
精确化地演变成了现在我们所知的萌
Many have cited Lum from the 1978 manga others say Urusei Yatsura
许多人提到了1978年开始连载的漫画福星小子 中的拉姆
has been the progenitor of Moe as we know it and possibly the very first Waifu.
同时是萌和二次元老婆两个概念的创始人
A very cute and innocent character at first glance
第一眼看上去是天真无邪且十分可爱的角色
but one with a fiery temper who refers to the main protagonist as darling.
同时脾气十分火爆 又觉得男主角是自己的Darling宝贝
Hmm.
发出了DARLING in the FRANXX的声音.aac
She's often credited as being the first Tsundere.
她同时也被认为是傲娇始祖
So it comes as no surprise that she's such an important an iconic character in the medium
所以意料之中的是 她成为了动画史上的重要名人
but of course at the time this was just a new character trait audiences responded well too.
但当时也只是被当作一种能让观众反响强烈新的角色性格而已
And she certainly wasn't created for the purpose of being a Waifu.
当然她也不是以二次元老婆的目的创造出来的
This would also be seen in characters like Lynn Minmay from the original SDF Macross.
类似的角色还有超时空要塞 最初的那一部中的角色林明美
A dear that many traces we've seen popular female characters nowadays
同样也可以在现在的女性角色里找到很多类似的特征
as well as being one of the earliest Idol characters
同时还是最早的偶像类角色
that just happens to be in a Mecha show.
不过是在机甲动画里的
And at the time with far more focus on the Mecha side of things.
那时大家都更关注机甲动画的题材
In terms of the whole design and aesthetics we can see a lot of influence from Bishoujo designs
可以看出整体的美学设计受到了美少女 人设的巨大影响
which have had its own evolution throughout the history of anime
美少女这个设定同样在动画史上有自己的演变
but of course for the show that would really popularize the aspects we would come to know in modern Moe
当然 提到真正把现代萌元素传播开来的动画
it would be hard to argue against Bishoujo Senshi Sailor Moon.
肯定是美少女战士
Considering how much of an international success this show was,
考虑到这个动画在国际社会的成功
think about how much it has in common with modern Moe shows today.
想想它和现代萌系动画的相似之处到底有多少
吐槽: 地场卫: ???
A full cast of varied female characters in an entirely feminine art style
全部角色(?)都是各不相同的女性 而且全部是女性化的艺术风格
that actually had a large male audience.
确实有着大量男性观众
The Shojo shows of the 80s and 90s with a significant male audience
80和90年代那些有着大量男性观众的少女动画
was a major turning point in the development of the Moe concept.
是萌元素发展的巨大转折点
These characters weren't there as fanservice eye candy or love i'nterest for the male protagonists.
这些角色不再是福利和杀必死 或者男主角的CP
They were the main focus of the show and that is how dedicated Moe shows operate now.
她们就是动画的中心 正如现在的萌系动画
Hell for Sailor Moon specifically some have even theorized the origin of the word Moe itself
特别是美少女战士 这个动画 甚至提出了萌 这个词的起源
came from Sailor Saturn Hotaru ToMoea.
来自水手土星土萌萤的名字
There are many other characters like these that either display modern Moe trace
还有很多其他类似的角色 展现出了现代萌元素的特性
or simply captured male audiences over the years.
或者仅仅是多年以来受男性观众的欢迎
But the last hugely important thing I want to mention influences extended beyond
不过最后一个我想提到的重要的影响是
just Moe is of course Neon Genesis Evangelion.
只是对萌元素的影响 没错 EVA
Yes once again I am mentioning Evangelion for the fuck.
我特么又提了一次EVA
I don't know just assume next time I'm talking about the evolution of an aspect within anime,
只是假设我下次提到另一个动画元素的发展的时候
Evangelion is gonna have some part in it.
也会讲到EVA 吧
And in this case let's just say Asuka and Rei are a big deal as far as Moe is concerned.
只是萌元素的话 肯定要提到明日香和绫波丽
They really changed the game as far as how audiences reacted to female characters.
她们极大地改变了观众对女性角色的反应
Audiences were deeply attached and loyal as well.
观众都深深地喜欢并忠于她们
This was arguably the first proper Waifu war.
颇具争议地是 这也是第一个真正意义上的二次元老婆战争
Just think about how many characters we've seen over the years that have been influenced by them.
只是想想这些年来被她们影响的角色到底有多少
It was at this point in the 90s that the character archetypes we know today were firmly solidified
也是从90年代的这动画开始 我们现在所知道的动画人物套路都被确定下来了
and more importantly what Evangelion proved was the franchising power of it.
更重要的是 EVA 证明了品牌的力量 痞子是有多么会利用品牌来骗钱
Everything was franchised in EVA including its Waifu who's still to this day.
EVA 中的一切都可以拿来营销 包括这动画里时髦至今的二次元老婆
And it is this financial success that is important to note.
也就是这种金融上的成功需要特别留意 此种骗钱天才需要重点关照
Because in all these shows whilst many of them had great stories,
因为在所有这些动画里 尽管它们中的许多有着很好的故事
it was the audience connection to the characters that made them as big as they were.
但是 只有观众和角色之间的联系才能让它们闻名远扬
The simple idea of an intimate personal attachment towards a character
仅仅是观众对角色的喜爱这件事 就会极大地影响萌元素的演变
would play a massive role in the evolution of the concept
because this meant fan base investment.
因为这意味着粉丝经济
The more a fan cares about a show or even a single specific aspect or character of that show
一个粉丝哪怕只是更加关心动画的一个具体方面或者具体角色而非动画的全部
the more likely they are to invest into the franchise as a whole.
就有更大地可能在整个动画品牌上花钱
It's turned the characters themselves into a marketable brands
这将动画角色自身转变为可以市场营销的品牌
and companies would slowly realize how profitable this was.
而这些公司也将缓慢地认识到这是多么有利润
In all genres branding plays a huge role in the success of a given show.
无论是什么题材 品牌的设计都对它的成功起到了很大作用
And by capitalizing on the emotional response, these shows were able to thrive.
而通过充分利用这些感情上的反应 这些动画将会繁荣发展
Be it through merchandising home video sales or whatever else.
通过推销碟子或者别的什么商品
As time progressed to the early 2000s, we would continue seeing trace of Moe across the board
到了00年代 我们能看到萌元素在某些动画中全面地出现
in shows like Azumanga Daioh.
譬如阿滋漫画大王 这样的动画
But it was a small part of a larger whole.
但这只是一小部分
Moe certainly was present throughout anime
萌元素确实是动画中的元素
but it wasn't as recognized or as prevalent in the culture.
但是文化中还不那么盛行 也不为人所知
It was simply one aspect you'd find in anime.
只是动画中的一个方面
You could point to the odd character having cute in quirky aspects.
你会发现奇怪的角色在奇怪的方面有着奇怪的可爱
We had our established character archetypes.
我们有着几种角色套路
But no one yet had come along to fully take advantage of the franchising potential
但是没人充分发挥
Moe could give to a property.
这些品牌上的萌潜力
This was all about to change however with one studio
差不多就要改变的时候到了
that would explode onto the scene.
但是一家公司的出现了
Downright perfecting the modern formula, leading to a change felt across the medium
完善了萌的现代方案 改变了萌在动画中的地位
that we still see today.
正如我们现在看到的这样
The revolution was about to begin.
革命亟待开始
京都动画的崛起
Whilst the true origins of Moe are widely debatable,
尽管萌的起源总是广受争议
I'm sure we can all agree that was the show's created by Kyoto Animation in the mid to late 2000s
我认为有件事我们能达成一致 就是一个00年代下半叶由京都动画 制作的动画
that cemented the concept in the mainstream anime consensus.
这个动画加强了萌元素的主流动画共识
Before the full on Moe powerhouse Kyoto Animation is known for today,
在京都动画 因出产大量萌系动画出名之前
you may remember though it wasn't always this way.
你也许还记得它制作过别的动画
Well started as a small animation studio based in Kyoto,
发家自京都的一个小型动画工作室
wait wait can someone fact check that for me please.
等下 能让人帮我核实一下这个信息吗
They would get their first big break in making spin-off to a Mecha series.
他们获得的第一次大机遇是制作一个机甲系列的衍生动画
注: 事实上全金属狂潮的第四作全金属狂潮 Invisible Victory 在2018年4月上映，第三作TSR并不是最终作
Full Metal Panic? Fumoffu! and then its eventual sequel The Second Raid
全金属狂潮？Fumoffu 和它的最终作全金属狂潮TSR
and in 2005 would also release Air.
还有在2005年上映的Air TV版
It's this period where we started to see the rise of shows
也就是这段时间 我们开始看到那种
with the more recognized more modern Moe style that we have now
有着更像是现代萌风格的动画
and this would lay the groundwork for their next show
这也就为他们的下一个动画打下了基础
which would truly solidify the oncoming revolution.
这个动画真的定义了接下来的革命
Change was coming and it was in the form of a bossy brunettes high school girl who was a god literally.
改变正在发生 以一个褐色头发的蛮横高中女孩 同时又是神的形式 真der
The Melancholy of Haruhi Suzumiya blasted onto screens in 2006.
凉宫春日的忧郁 在2006年冲击性地上映
And Haruhi stamped down her presence which was felt across the whole community.
凉宫当时在动画粉丝团体中产生了重大的影响
Anyone around just over ten years ago
10年前的动画粉丝
well remember how much of a cultural phenomenon this was for our community
会记得这在当时刮起了多大的文化风潮
because the whole quirkiness of the show was something that we hadn't really seen before.
这个动画的古怪性质是我们之前所未能见过的
Before anime was known for its futuristic cyberpunk
未来派的赛博朋克
giant robots, shonen fights and then seemingly overnight,
大机器人 少年战斗题材曾代表了动画 而几乎是在一夜之间
everyone was doing a synchronized dance to a hyperactive J pop song
每个人都在跟着活跃的日本流行音乐同步跳着团舞
starting religions around a high school girl and scouting people for the SOS Brigade.
围绕着高中女生展开宗教活动并为SOS团招募成员
It wasn't just about Haruhi.
不只是关于凉宫
It was about to buying into her ethos.
而是关于认同她的价值观
Haruhi wasn't just another anime girl.
凉宫不再是另一个普通的动画女角色
Haruhi was a God and she was your God one whom you must obey.
凉宫是一个你必须信奉的神
You had high school girl Haruhi, bunny girl Haruhi, bunny girl Haruhi with a guitar.
这包括了高中女生凉宫 兔耳娘凉宫 拿着吉他的兔耳娘凉宫
A catchy dance only dedicated fans would be able to pull off.
一个流行舞蹈只有热情的粉丝才会跳
And Aya Hirano, who was catapulted into superstar status.
而凉宫的配音平野绫 则一举成名 甚至达到了明星的程度
Everything about this show was franchised marketed and sold.
所有这个动画的元素都被拿去做市场营销了
The show created his own culture
这个动画创造了自己的文化
and people bought into it. People bought into it in spades.
而人们对此深信不疑
The success of the show skyrocketed Moe into the forefront of the anime consensus.
这个动画的成功迅速将萌元素拉入动画共识的首位
I mean I know this was my first show where I learned what Moe was.
我指的是我是从这个动画了解到什么是萌
In this situation Moe is an important concept to keep in mind.
在这种情况下萌是需要记住的重要概念
Sorry, what'd you say?
对不起 你刚刚说了啥
Moe was in. Moe was profitable.
萌变得时尚 萌变得有利可图
And Haruhi became a symbol of the fan base investment into this quirky anime girl culture.
而喜欢萌元素这种奇怪的动画女孩文化的粉丝们则将凉宫当成他们的符号
And I think this was due to a partially being self-aware
我认为这一部分来自粉丝对于萌元素的自我认识
and partially celebrating everything it was being self-aware about.
而另一部分则来自于庆祝获得了萌元素的自我认识
But Kyoto Animation didn't stop there.
但是京都动画 并不止于此
They continued their history of adapting Key shows
他们持续制作Key社 作品的改编动画
with the Canon Remake in late 2006 and of course Clannad.
包括2006年晚些时候的Kanon重制版 以及Clannad
Both of which have a great deal of Moe elements in their own rights.
在他们可改编的权利之下 这两者都有很多萌元素
But it would be the release of Lucky Star that fully encapsulated everything we now expect of Moe shows.
但是直到幸运☆星 的发布才完全概括了我们现在所指的萌系动画的方方面面
Lucky Stars all levels of popularity equal or even exceeding that of Haruhi .
幸运☆星 的人气等同甚至超过了凉宫春日
A show but a group of schoolgirls really just being cute and hanging out.
一个关于一组可爱的女学生随处逛逛的动画
Something which a young 18 year old Gigguk at the time did not get in his second ever video on YouTube.
18岁的年轻Gigguk在他油管的第二个视频里甚至没有理解这个动画
I still kind of don't really get it.
我现在还是有点没搞懂
Well this show did was take one of the elements fans liked about Haruhi.
不过这个动画确实从凉宫那里拿去了一些粉丝们喜欢的元素
The cute girls, relatable main character, the high school setting and amped up the Moe aspect.
可爱的女孩 能引起共鸣的主角 高中设定和最关键的萌元素
It proved that you didn't need sci-fi twist to engage an audience.
证明你不需要科幻转折来吸引观众
Audiences could find a connection even if there wasn't a big overarching plot
观众一样能找到共鸣 就算没有宏大的剧情
and with it the momentum Kyoto Animation gained from releasing these shows back was enormous.
随着这样的势头发展下去 京都动画 从中获得的收益是巨大的
They had set the stage.
他们架好了舞台
Moe was growing rapidly and they were right at the forefront of it.
萌元素迅速发展起来了 而他们就处在首位
Everything they touched seemed to turn into gold.
所有他们碰到的作品似乎都变成了黄金作品
What they didn't know was what they touched next would turn into pure diamond.
不过他们并不知道他们触及的下一个作品成为了真正的钻石级经典
When we think of influential shows in the history of anime,
当我们讲到动画历史中有影响力的那些动画
we think of international manga hits like Akira, Evangelion and Dragon Ball Z.
我们会想到那些在国际上有冲击力的动画如阿基拉 EVA 和龙珠Z
Anime that had an wide effect and influenced their genres for years to come.
那些广为传播并影响了多年的题材的动画
注: 参考七年前视频av520597，youtu.be/Jf3VEoyHsAA
So seven years after some no name on the internet reviewed K-ON!
所以在某个无名小辈评测轻音少女 的七年之后
and publicly exclaimed that this was a nothing show about cute girls drinking motherfucking tea.
而他当时公开声称这个动画只不过是关于可爱的女孩们喝着他娘的茶的故事
I can now regardingly admit that
对此我表示
K-ON! is one of the most important and influential shows to come out for modern anime.
对现代动画而言 轻音少女 是最具影响力且最重要的动画之一
Yeah those were really words that just came out of my mouth.
没错那些话我确实说过
Motherfucking tea.
他娘的茶
K-ON! was the final evolution character animation has set in a path they started.
轻音少女 是京都动画 动画角色革命路线图上设定的最后一步
While Haruhi he could still be seen as a high school comedy with sci-fi twist
当凉宫可以看成是有着科幻转折的高中喜剧
and Lucky Star could be seen as a slice of life high school comedy
而幸运☆星 可以看作是反映生活的高中喜剧
in the same vein as Azumanga Daioh just with a very very strong Moe element,
和阿滋漫画大王 类似的风格 不过是具有了特别强的萌元素
K-ON! wasn't really any of those.
轻音少女 和它们并不类似
It was just Moe.
它只是萌
And it was the first time people started calling an entire show as such.
而且也是人们第一次把一部作品完全用萌来概括
This was something the community hadn't seen before.
这是动画社区之前从未见过的东西
The main selling point wasn't its ground plot points.
它的主要卖点不是作为基础的剧情
It wasn't its god-busting comedy, romance or action.
(不像凉宫那样)是什么虐神喜剧 爱情或者动作
It was just the fluffy feeling of being able to hang with cute cuddly anime girls.
只是那种和可爱柔软的动画女生一起玩的轻盈感觉
Sure it had its music but that was never the main focus.
没错 它有音乐部分 但不是重点
Much to the dismay of many who didn't understand the show
对于那些没能理解这部动画的人可能会很沮丧
but the focus was on the chemistry shared between its characters.
关注点在于角色之间惺惺相惜的关系
Characters that individually may not seem like anything special
这些角色看起来没什么特别的
but for vast audiences the whole turned out to be much greater than the sum of its parts.
但是对于大多数观众而言 角色们整体带来的感觉比分隔开再相加要强很多
I'm probably not the best person to be able to tell you about what the appeal of K-ON! was.
我也许不是告诉你轻音少女 吸引力的最佳人选
but what I certainly can tell you about is its success.
但我能告诉你它的成功
Audiences felt a deep connection to these girls and it was primarily a male demographic too.
观众能和这些女生们感同身受 当然主要是男性观众的说法
From their designs to the girls personalities
从动画的设计到女生的性格设定
to the various scenarios they'd find themselves in to the chemistry that they all shared,
以及许多那些女生们分享相互之间默契的场景
K-ON! had perfected the Moe formulas so much.
轻音少女 完美地演绎了萌的方法
It found his success by just reveling in its own Moennis.
通过沉湎于自身的萌元素而获得了成功
注: 参考名作之壁京都动画 销量排行榜 av2482186，这里当然指的是总量
This would go on to become one of the highest selling Blu-ray releases for its time.
而这之后 轻音少女 变成了京都动画 蓝光最畅销的动画之一
K-ON! made Moe the biggest thing in anime after its release.
在它发布之后 轻音少女 让萌变成了动画中最关键的元素
It wasn't Mecha. It wasn't action or romance.
不再是机甲动画 不再是动作或者是恋爱动画
It was cute girls doing cute things and it changed the way we look at anime today.
只是可爱的女孩子做着可爱的事情 正如今天这样
K-ON! wasn't just popular.
轻音少女 不仅是火起来了
K-ON! didn't just cement Moe or start some kind of trend.
轻音少女 不仅是强化了萌元素 并引发了某种趋势
K-ON! down there created its own genre.
轻音少女 自己创造了一个题材
The evolution became a revolution.
萌的演化变成了萌的革命
更多的题材
What came next was a plethora of shows I can only describe as belonging in the Moe genre.
接下来就是一堆我只能描述成属于萌这个题材的动画
Now a lot of people myself included have referred to Moe as a genre before.
现在包括我自己在内 已经将萌称作一种题材
So let's just set the record straight and say definitively Moe isn't a genre technically.
所以我们现在还是直白地澄清一下事实 严格来说萌并不是一种题材
In the same way that Shonen isn't technically a genre but people often refer to it as one.
同样地 少年不是一种题材 但是人们把这个称呼为一种题材
Because of the trends and commonalities we find within the shows.
因为我们在这些动画里能找到相同的特征引起相同的风潮
In this case Moe describes the general theme and tone of the show and its characters.
同样地 萌描述的只是大体上的主题和动画还有动画角色的风格
For the most part a show someone would drop in this Moe genre
对于多数能归类到萌题材的动画
would likely just be a slice of life drama or comedy
差不多都是生活戏剧或者生活喜剧
but with how broad that definition is it doesn't really tell you what you need to know.
但是因为萌这个定义的宽泛性 你不能从中得知你想知道的东西
Planetes and Great Teacher Onizuka can also be described in that way
星空清理者 和麻辣教师GTO 也可以如此描述
but they sure as hell aren't Moe show's.
它们绝不会有萌系作品那样萌
K-ON! and Lucky Star may not have been the first examples of cute girls doing cute things
轻音少女 和幸运☆星 也许不是第一批可爱的女孩子做可爱的事情的动画
but they sure as hell cemented the concept into the mainstream.
但是它们给主流强化了萌的概念
And more importantly directed Moe down and more defines path
而更重要的是 针对性的萌动画数量减少了 而更多的动画找寻了别的出路
because it was sure has held these show successes that others try to emulate.
因为这些动画确实创造了那种别的动画想要效仿的成功
It was this new subset of slice of life series
在这种新的生活动画的派生集合当中
that would essentially purpose towards appealing to this cute Moe feeling.
目的根本上是为了激发这种萌感
As we discussed before Moe is a very broad term
正如我们之前所说的 萌是一种宽泛的概念
that is subjective for every individual.
定义因人而异
But what Kyoto Animation did was perfect of working formula.
京都动画 所做的不过是完善这种方法
It made Moe more targeted, more marketable.
让萌更具针对性 更具市场性
It was a tangible thing that other companies could try to replicate.
很显然 别的公司也想复制这种成功
You had the more rounded cuter art style, a bunch of character archetypes
你周围有了更多的可爱元素 一堆角色套路
and almost all female cast, little to no roam out scenarios you could put them in and a fresh new audience
以及角色几乎全是女性 把她们放在基本不动的场景里 还有一堆新的观众
and I found out this was a thing they wanted and would invest deeply in.
然后我发现这是他们想要的 也会深深投入的东西
You could even say this started a Moe arms race
你甚至可以说这开启了一场萌的军备竞赛
and one genre to benefit the most from this time period was of course Idol shows.
有一种题材从中获益最多 那就是偶像题材
Now Idol shows actually go back a pretty long way in anime
当然偶像动画有着很长的历史
but I don't think it's any surprise that the surge in popular Idol shows
但是对于偶像动画在轻音少女 开启萌系动画的繁荣之后的涌现
came in at time of the Moe boom that K-ON! started.
我觉得我们不必惊讶
As you can see how a successful formula have influenced the Idol genre.
你能发现这种成功方法对偶像题材的巨大影响
I mean what are the kind of shows would be able to thrive in an environment
我是还有哪种动画能在这种环境下蓬勃发展
where the audience wanted a core of pure innocent character archetypes being brought together,
这种环境指的就是观众希望能有一群纯粹无邪的角色类型团结起来
where we as an audience member can watch them bond and grow together.
并看着他们一点点团结成长的故事
IdolM@STER, LoveLive! these now mega popular franchises
偶像大师 LoveLive! 这些是十分具有人气的品牌
rose up in a post K-ON! era following the groundwork that it had lay.
在后轻音少女 时期发展起来 受益于轻音少女的坚实基础
Was it cute? Yes.
它可爱吗 可爱
Was it marketable? Fuck yes.
能卖得出去吗 都买爆了.jpg
Was their deep fanbase investment?
有粉丝的狂热投入吗
发出了死宅便秘的声音.aac
Are you fucking kidding me?
这不明摆着的吗 四斋蒸鹅心.jpg
Idol shows it still going strong and firmly establish themselves in their own genre.
偶像动画依然很强势 而且坚实地树立起了自身的题材
But while Moe has definitely had a strong influence there,
尽管萌元素肯定对偶像动画产生了很大影响
it also blew up in other places
它也影响了别的题材
but not everything has shared this same longevity.
但也不是所有动画的影响力都如此持久
萌的泛滥
During the height of the Moe boom,
在萌系作品的高峰时期
everyone wants to find the next cute girls doing cute things mega hit.
每个人都想找寻下一批可爱的女孩子做着可爱的事情让人身心愉悦
And while K-ON! had a deeper soul behind it the audience's latched on to,
虽然轻音少女 在这背后有着让观众很感兴趣的更深的内涵
the same cannot be said for others that tried jumping on this bandwagon.
其他跳入这种潮流的动画却很难说有这么深的吸引观众的内涵
The term Moe blob was coined on the simple criticisms of characters in these vanilla shows
萌肥皂剧 这个新词指的就是对这种乏味动画的纯粹批评
feeling samey and pandering.
这些动画让人感到千篇一律和阿谀奉承
A Moe blob is just there as a character that's meant to be Moe for the audience
萌肥皂剧 指的是那些就是打算给观众展示萌的角色
and sometimes ends up feeling way too obvious and completely falls flat.
有时让人感觉太过明显 而且过于僵化
The core concept of shows trying to pander to Moe tropes exclusively quickly annoyed audiences
这种只是千篇一律地展现萌的特点的概念很快就惹恼了观众
because they were more than sick of seeing it.
因为他们对此感到了厌烦
So now much like with Idol shows,
就像偶像动画一样
the industry had to find creative and unique ways to make these shows feel fresh and interesting.
业界需要找到一种更具独特创意的方法来让这些动画变得新鲜而有趣
You can't just have cute girls doing cute things anymore you see.
你不能只是让可爱的女孩子们做着可爱的事情
You've got to have cute girls doing other things.
你需要让可爱的女孩子们做点别的事
吐槽: 我永远喜欢魔法少女俺.jpg 哪怕连很可爱地做都不是
So long as they're doing it cutely.
只要她们还是很可爱地做
So now we've got fine examples like cute girls doing airsoft.
所以现在我们就能找到一些不错的例子 譬如可爱的女孩子们玩生存游戏
Cute girls doing game design.
可爱的女孩子们做着游戏设计
吐槽: 此处应有攻壳机动队ARISE，骑着摩托车的萌版平胸少佐.jpg
Cute girls doing motorbike racing.
可爱的女孩子们进行摩托车比赛
Cute girls doing tankery.
可爱的女孩子干着坦克活
Wait. That's... that's not a fucking word you idiot.
诶 等等 没有坦克活这个词
Cute girls doing amazing things that we'll never be able to achieve in our lifetime.
可爱的女孩子们做着奇特的事情 甚至是那些我们一生中都不可能做到的事情
because we're stuck here watching some video documenting the history of cute anime girls.
因为我们只是卡在这里看着什么记录动画萌妹子历史的视频
发出了真嗣的声音.aac
注: 参见EVA 恶搞第一期av514500, youtu.be/vtUpWihJJJ4, 虽然我知道不是Gigguk配的真嗣, 但是很像
But that's just natural evolution Moe had to take.
但这只是萌元素的自然发展过程
Purely Moe blob shows are becoming a less common thing in this day and age
纯萌肥皂剧 现在越来越少见
but in this place you have these shows taking Moe elements
但是现在你看到一些使用萌元素的动画
but adding an extra hook to appeal to audiences with specific interests.
但是加入其他能吸引人的特定元素
And that brings us to the latest form of Moe shows in modern anime.
这就是现代动画中最新形式的萌系动画
Let's say you wanted to make a Moe show with a hook for people who are interested in ships.
譬如 我们设想一种萌系动画是给那些喜欢船的人看的
注: 能想到的是高校舰队 和苍蓝钢铁的琶音
Well what if we make the girls pilot the ships.
那么 我们设想一种女孩子们开船的动画
No! The girls are the ships.
不 船本身就是女孩子
You are a fucking genius.
你他娘的真是个天才
Anthropomorphism is the current big trend besides Idols in Moe anime.
除却萌系动画中的偶像元素 拟人化思想是当前一大趋势
吐槽: 页游也算mobile game吗，好吧也算至少有个安卓版
The immense success of the Kantai Collection mobile game could be easily seen as partly responsible for this
舰队Collection游戏的巨大成功肯定推动了这一趋势
so whether they're boats, guns, horses or fucking household appliances
所以不管它们是船 枪 马 还是家用器具
these are the levels Moe shows need to go to these days for people to pay attention to them.
这些事萌系动画吸引观众观看而需要达到的水平
But here's the thing even though we can point to the evolution of Moe a show specifically
但即使我们能指出萌系动画的演变历程
Idols, slice of life or Anthropomorphism,
譬如偶像 生活或者拟人化题材
the effects of it can be seen in the much wider anime landscape.
也能在更广泛的动画题材中找到萌系的影响
In recent years we've become so accustomed to seeing it
最近几年我们都习以为常
that it's just become a normal part of anime now.
萌元素也成为了动画的正常部分
And to me that is the final evolution of what Moe a has become in this modern era.
对我而言这就是萌元素在现代的最终演变
萌的未来
Ever since K-ON! and its predecessors in some way or another Moe has crept into the modern anime landscape
自从轻音少女 和它的前身以某种方式代表着萌系动画悄悄进入现代动画图景之后
in a way unlike any other trends that came before it.
以一种不同于以往的趋势出现
In the Mecha video we talked about
在机甲动画那一期中
how its evolution directly influenced decades of a genre and eventually died down.
它的演变如何影响数十年以来的机甲题材 并最终减弱
Moe hasn't done that.
萌系动画还没走完这个流程
Moe hasn't separated itself into an exclusive Moe genre.
萌系动画甚至还没有发展到单独的题材
It's done quite the opposite.
恰恰相反
Instead it has spread throughout the entire medium as we know it
它在我们所知的所有动画中传播开来
and become synonymous with anime itself
甚至和动画相伴相生
and what I find so interesting
我发现有一点很有趣
is that this change in landscape happened within my lifespan of my anime fandom.
就是这种改变发生在我入坑动画以后的时间里
It's not something I read about or her people talk about in the past.
并不是我在书里看到的或者是听别人讲到过去的故事
I saw it happen.
我见证了它的发生
A lot of us saw it happen.
很多人也见证了它的发生
Moe feels like it's always been there.
萌元素感觉更像是已经发生过的事
Sure there was a time when we became more aware of it
当然以后肯定会有一个我们更加了解它的时期
and many believe there is a trend that's come and gone.
而且很多人认为这不过是另一个来了又会走的风潮而已
But it hasn't gone anywhere.
但是它还没走
It's just slipped between the cracks and taken over a huge part of the identity of what anime is today.
它不过是溜到了题材之间的缝隙当中 并给予了当前动画新的特征
The influence of Moe is in almost every genre of modern anime.
萌几乎影响了所有的现代动画
Anime characters have learned how to be much more direct in targeting that specific Moe feeling.
动画人物的性格需要更直接地以特定的萌为目标进行塑造
Even if the characters themselves aren't designed to be Moe.
即使动画角色人设本来不是萌的
Everyone has a cute quirk.
每个人都有点古怪地可爱
Every girl needs a unique selling point even if it's just something completely surface level.
每个女孩都需要一些独特的卖点 哪怕只是表面装样子
吐槽: Gigguk这个解说配合画面是铁了心黑小埋啊，连卖萌都要吐槽不专业，表面卖萌.jpg
We're in a time when female characters that trend aren't necessarily the deepest or most fleshed out.
当前这个时代 女性角色并不需要有多内涵或者充实
They're the ones with the most unique gimmick.
她们不过是有着最独特的噱头
The ones whose designs more stand out.
设计出来只是为了更夺人眼球
For you see because the concept of Moe can be applied to any show,
你可以看到 萌这个概念可以运用到很多动画上面
it now almost does apply to every show.
现在确实几乎运用到了所有动画上
Whether directly an obvious or simply then the background of some characters
不管是直着来明着来还是仅仅只是背景里的几个配角
who act in a way we just expect characters to act now,
正如我们期待地那样表现
Moe is the norm even if you're not specifically a fan of Moe shows.
萌元素成了某种准则 就算你不喜欢萌元素
吐槽: 毕竟还有乙女向和腐女向甚至男性向共有的可爱的男孩子要素
毕竟前面剪辑里已经有很多冰上的尤里 的镜头了
Some of you may think I'm overdramatizing the impact of these cute anime girls
有些人可能认为我过分夸大了这些可爱动画女孩的影响力
but the thing is these aren't just cute anime girls.
事实是这些不仅仅是可爱的动画女孩
They're brands.
她们还是品牌
They're marketable products that can be commoditized and sold
这些市场营销的产品可以被商品化并卖出
and we proudly buy into it.
而我们会很自豪地买账
It's a million dollar franchise,
它是数百万刀的品牌
注: 参见上一期二次元老婆的科学av27354481
is a fashionable art style, is something for us to argue over, who is cuter, who is better, who is best.
也是时尚的艺术潮流 让我们对此争议 谁更可爱 谁更强 谁最好
They have become as much of a symbol for our medium, as giant robots and muscly action heroes were in the past.
就像以前动画的大机器人和肌肉动作戏主角一样 现在也成为了动画的符号
and continue to be an integral part of the culture that we love.
也将持续性地变为我们喜爱的文化中必要的一部分
That's what I mean when I say was a revolution.
这就是我所说我所指的革命
Because it was a successful one.
因为萌系成功了
Moe may have always existed in one form or another
萌元素在各种形式下都存在
but now it is at the forefront,
但现在变成了最明显的部分
stamping down its mark on the medium without going anywhere anytime soon.
在动画领域打下烙印而非很快地消失
It was a Moe uprising.
这是萌的兴起
It was a Moe takeover.
这是萌的统治
It was a Moe revolution.
这是萌的革命
So quick announcement.
接下来简短地声明一下
It felt good going through my old videos in the process of making this my own video.
制作这期视频的时候 回顾以前的老视频让我愉悦
And just seeing my older shitty videos
只是看着以前的辣鸡视频
and we got the idea to make a motherfucking tea mug based on my original K-ON! video
我就想根据我最初的轻音少女 视频做一个喝他娘的茶马克杯
for the three people that actually remember it.
为那三个真的还记得这件事的人做的
See if you want to grab this what I think is probably like my first og meme my ever made.
这个差不多就是我做的第一个黑话梗
Back like, Jesus, seven years ago.
天哪 过去了差不多七年了
Then I'll put a link in the description.
想要这个杯子的人可以去简介看一下
It's gonna be a limited time thing cuz I don't think many people are gonna remember it.
这是限时的 因为我觉得不会有很多人记得这件事
It'll be up for like two weeks till the fourth of August.
差不多两周时间 到8月4号
So get one more you can because I'm not gonna leave that for long.
你想买的话可以考虑一下 以后就没了
I don't think many people are gonna even remember of this.
我还是觉得我需要再说一次很多人不会记得这件事
And you don't even need to drink tea out of it.
而且你也不需要拿它喝茶
I'm drinking coffee right now.
我现在在喝咖啡
Just don't tell anyone.
不要告诉任何人
But with that said thank you very much to
不提这些了 感谢以下人士
And everyone else a patron for helping to support me for this month and making this video possible.
以及任何其他这个月在patreon上支持我的人 没有你们无法做出这期视频
The videos like these that require the most time research and resources.
像这样的视频需要很多时间制作
So I would not be able to do bigger projects like these without your support on there
所以没有你们的支持真的不能做到如此大的工程
especially if these don't do as well but I always love working on them.
哪怕这些视频不会有以前那么高的点击量 但我还是喜欢做这样的视频
Not sure what my next big genre breakdown is gonna be just yet
不知道我的下一个题材会在哪时火起来
but I'm gonna be excited to work on it.
不过我会持续工作的
Anyway that's it for me
不管怎么说 今天先到这儿
if you want the limited time mug go click a link in the description.
如果你要这个限时马克杯 记得点简介里的链接
And otherwise I've been Gigguk, and I will see you all next time!
下次再见